<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alexchace.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alexchace.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-27T00:00:26-04:00</updated><id>https://alexchace.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex Chace</title><subtitle>Ph.D. student, Moving Image Studies, Georgia State University.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Barriers to Motherhood: Biotechnology, Reproductive Justice, and Transgender Women</title><link href="https://alexchace.com/barriers_to_motherhood/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Barriers to Motherhood: Biotechnology, Reproductive Justice, and Transgender Women" /><published>2018-11-09T07:50:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-09T07:50:00-05:00</updated><id>https://alexchace.com/barriers_to_motherhood</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexchace.com/barriers_to_motherhood/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was originally presented at the National Women’s Studies Association conference&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ### Abstract --&gt;
&lt;!-- Reproductive activism has typically focused on abortion and pregnancy over other concerns, thereby centering white cisgender women and (increasingly) transgender men. Even trans-inclusive discourse has paid relatively little attention to the reproductive needs and possibilities of transgender women, particularly trans women of color. Accordingly, this paper analyzes how medicalized discourses, unequal access to healthcare, and cissexism intersect to discursively, medically, and legally deny motherhood to transgender women. Furthermore, it envisions contested futures where biotechnologies and reproductive trans bodies trouble &quot;the coherence of a narrative that is already fragile&quot; while potentially perpetuating existing inequities (Strangio 2015, p. 235). --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feminist reproductive activism has historically focused narrowly on cisgender women and their reproductive concerns - access to contraception, abortion, and so on. Many feminists and trans activists, however, have and continue to push reproductive rights discourse on the issue of trans inclusion, with some success. If you recall, Planned Parenthood’s Indiana/Kentucky branch caused some controversy back in march for a tweet which reads “Some men have a uterus”, repeated about 11 times. This has been a hot issue in the blogosphere for some time as well. In a 2016 article for the Huffington Post, “activist, advocate, [and] blogger” Tory Smith (those are their words) argues for an approach to trans activism that moves beyond visibility and representation and onto issues of reproductive justice in the trans context. But while Smith speaks of ‘trans people’ and the ‘trans community’, and indeed quotes statistics on anti-trans discrimination undivided by assigned sex or gender identity, it becomes clear in the end that his primary concern is trans men’s experience of pregnancy and their access to gynecological care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To move into more academic discussions, Laura Nixon’s 2013 article, &lt;em&gt; The Right to (Trans) Parent: A Reproductive Justice Approach to Reproductive Rights, Fertility, and Family-Building Issues Facing Transgender People&lt;/em&gt;, gives an overview of trans reproductive rights concerns and points of potential coalitional building. Nixon details a broad series of reproductive concerns, but her primary focus is still on transgender men, and while she does name trans women in particular, it is only very briefly in a bigger conversation around cryopreservation of fertility that promptly refocuses itself onto transgender men, particularly issues relating to the uterus - abortion, pregnancy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often see that, although the scope of reproductive justice has widened to include transgender people, it remains somewhat unspecified to &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; trans people these discourses refer. Many efforts at trans inclusion do so based on the assumption that reproductive rights mainly concern the rights and freedoms of people with uteri, and, like most other reproductive rights discourse, the concerns of affluent and white people are centered. As trans male activist Chase Strangio explains, trans reproductive justice for him, as “a white trans man; a lawyer; and a person with access to wealth and resources… means that [he] may choose not to become pregnant or that [he] worr[ies] about the embarrassment of being scrutinized at the gynecologist”. Transversely, for trans women of color, “it means devastating rates of murder, forced sterilization, incarceration” (Strangio 2015, 224)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I ask: what remains left unsaid, in this utero-centric discourse, for transgender women? By focusing on trans women, and trans people assigned male at birth more broadly, I am not suggesting that trans men and trans people assigned female at birth are inappropriate in their reproductive concerns, or that these concerns do not deserve space within reproductive justice movements. Rather, I am suggesting that there is more to the story of trans reproductive justice, and more opportunities for coalitional forms of reproductive justice that destabilize normative discourses of reproductivity. My hope is that, by focusing on transgender women, we may see opportunities for genital and/or gamete-agnostic reproductive activism, casting a larger net of potential co-collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;barriers-to-trans-motherhood&quot;&gt;Barriers to Trans Motherhood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to begin with an overview of some of the ways transgender women become parents, and the challenges inherent to each method. These include: adoption, sexual intercourse with a partner who has a uterus, becoming a step-parent, and through assisted reproductive technology, namely insemination of a partner’s uterus with the trans woman’s cryopreserved sperm, or insemination of a partner’s uterus with a donor’s cryopreserved sperm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When trans women, especially teenagers, begin Hormone Replacement Therapy, one of the biggest concerns is the potentially sterilizing effects of estrogen-based hormone therapy and puberty blocker regimens. This is particularly true of trans teenagers, and this loss of fertility remains a hot-button issue in cultural discourses of trans children. For many trans women, spermatogenesis stops completely shortly after beginning hormone therapy, and it is unknown and whether spermatogenesis returns for all trans women after “prolonged estrogen treatment” or not (Wierckx et al, 2012). For trans girls prescribed puberty blockers prior to the onset of masculinizing puberty, spermatogenesis never begins in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anxiety around trans girls’ reproductive capacity centers around the “unknown” regarding the long-term use of HRT’s effects on future reproductive ability. But what is invariable in trans health is that is that sex reassignment surgery “results in an irreversible loss of natural reproductive capacity in transsexual women” (Wierckx et al, 2012). I mention this because legal recognition often depends on surgical status - medicalized narratives determine not only who receives medical treatment, but also who receives legal recognition of their sex on major identity documents and vital records, including driver’s licenses and birth certificates. Policies vary state-by-state, and are often arbitrary, vague, and/or inconsistent, but almost all require some type of medical “approval” prior to legal recognition. Medical approval, in many states, means surgical intervention (calling for vaginoplasty or phalloplasty, though others are non-specific), thereby compelling trans people to submit to the rules of medical practice whether they desire genital surgery or not (“Changing Birth Certificate Sex Designations: State-By-State Guidelines” n.d.). And although medical intervention is required, medical coverage of trans healthcare is inconsistent at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposition that young trans girls should not be allowed to transition due to fertility concerns is directly at odds with the reality of trans reproductive oppression. Trans girls are discouraged/disallowed from transitioning in order to keep their fertility, but if and when they do transition, they are thrown into a system which demands sterilization as the prerequisite of legal recognition. The prospect of trans motherhood is thus rendered impossible, because the stakes of legal recognition are dire. Desutter (as cited in Wierckx et al 2012, 107) found that, even though “51% of their study group [of transgender women]…would have considered sperm freezing or would have actually chosen to do so it if they had been offered”, 90% of their group “stated that fertility loss was not an important reason to defer their transition process” (as cited in Wierckx et al 2012, 1070). However, I believe it bears considering the obstacles that trans women face when they do choose to cryopreserve their sperm. The most notable obstacle is cost: aside from an “upfront cost of several hundred dollars”, cryopreservation of sperm also requires recurring annual fees costing hundreds of dollars (Nixon 2013, 97). For those who want to become parents, sperm-freezing is a long-term financial commitment, and for those with unstable incomes or limited funds this may be considered an undue burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For trans women that cannot or do not want to cryopreserve their sperm, donor sperm can be used to inseminate a partner’s uterus. But access to donor sperm is not universal, and opens up entirely new avenues of discrimination, and the discourses around donor insemination are not kind to trans women in particular. In 2003, Patricia Baetens et al. tackled the question: &lt;em&gt;Should requests for donor insemination on social grounds be expanded to transsexuals?&lt;/em&gt; In that article, they distinguish between two “subgroups” of trans women, “early presenting males”, primarily attracted to men, and “later-presenting males”, who are characterized as having a history of “transvestite fetishism” and are attracted to women. Trans men, on the other hand, are characterized as “[a]dult females with gender dysphoria”, who “are comparable to early-presenting males and almost invariably experience same-sex attraction”, i.e. attraction to women (Baetens et al. 2003, 283). They continue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although long-term follow-up research of adult transsexuals is limited, it appears that female-to-male transsexuals show fewer psychological disturbances, less psychopathology, have more stable relationships with the female partner, are socially better integrated and have a better economic outcome, and it can therefore be argued that treatment should be limited initially to female-to-male transexuals with a female partner. (Baetens et al 2003, 283).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their opinion, trans men “seem to be less at risk [than trans women] for psychiatric impairment” (Baetens et al 2003, 283). While 2003 was 15 years ago, the notion that trans women are improper or unsuited for motherhood is pervasive, and directly affects the experience of trans women as parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the actual process of becoming a parent, there is also the issue of how trans parents are treated - and to what degree they are allowed to be parents - after having children. Faccio et al. (2013) interviewed trans female and cis male parents about their thoughts on trans female parenthood. Cis men’s responses “indicated a belief that transsexual parents are incompetent…view[ing] transsexuality as even contrary to nature and as socially marginalized (‘It’s a little abnormal. It’s plainly abnormal’, ‘You’re going against nature’, ‘It’s not normal … because what God has given must be and remain’)” (Faccio et al 2013, 1062-1063). The male responses “reveal concern about the healthy growth of children and centre on the assumed psychological harm” (Faccio et al. 2013, 1063). In trans women’s responses, meanwhile, we see that trans women “were aware that they were considered ‘sick’, ‘crazy’, ‘confused’, and ‘incapable of raising a child’ by others” (Faccio et al 2013, 1063). Faccio et al. (2013) quotes Erika, a 58 year-old trans woman, explaining that “[t]he implied concept of transsexuality is sterility: That is, you have a right to gender change if you have your gonads taken out. That’s the idea . . . the basic reason giving you the right to change your documents is sterility” (Faccio et al. 2013, 58).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an article from 2015, Gail Hammer provides a case study of Kim, a trans female parent who transitioned after the birth of her children, eventually leading to the end of her marriage with her now ex-wife. Hammer (2015) explains that Kim was “ordered to pay more in child support than she earned”, and that when she was unable to pay, a court threw her into jail. While Kim was in jail, “she was dressed in a woman’s uniform, paraded through every part of the men’s population, and then held in solitary confinement in the wing for violent male offenders” (Hammer 2015, 119). Kim, who was unable to find employment due to anti-trans woman discrimination, was ordered to to pay $994 a month in child support. Although she was imputed to have a net income of $1,800 per month, Kim had never had such an income, even prior to transitioning and had recently chose to pursue her education using federal loan money (Hammer 2015, 124). Hammer explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The commissioner directed Kim to get a job and commented that Kim’s education was a luxury. The commissioner ordered Kim to “dress as a male” during contact with the children. Though she did not know the children in this case, the commissioner apparently assumed that, by definition, she knew what was best for the children, and that it would be best for the children to avoid confronting the complexity of their parent’s transgender status (Hammer 2015, 125).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nondisruptive-potentials&quot;&gt;(Non)disruptive Potentials&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Strangio (2015), “[t]he reality for trans people in reproductive rights discourse is that our bodies complicate the coherence of a narrative that is already fragile because of the fraught and unsettled nature of the legal protection at stake” (Strangio, 235). But the narrative of reproduction, and life itself, is fundamentally biopolitical. In this regime of reproductive control, trans people are targeted, without evidence, for forced sterilization and eugenics. When they do manage to become parents, their parenthood is contested, and their children may be taken away. Trans people are, thus, considered a “threat” to the prevailing cisheteronormative narrative of parenthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her controversial article, first published in August, Lisa Littman describes trans identity as a “social and peer contagion” that passes between members of a peer group (Littman 2018). The notion of transness as a contagion runs deep, and the idea that trans individuals are “sick”, or that their mere presence, especially for trans women, is a danger to a child’s psyche contributes to a certain discourse that frames trans identity in pathogenic terms. As with many other diseases, there is therefore no greater tragedy than to “pass on” transness to children. While other diseases are communicated via blood, sex, physical proximity, and reproduction, so too it is feared that trans identity could work just the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look to the future, we often imagine new technologies that will ‘fix’ the problems of today. And indeed, biotechnological and surgical techniques may someday allow for trans women to gestate their own children with a surgically transplanted uterus, or it may allow for trans women who are post-transition to (re)create gametes via gametogenesis. Both of these may be far off, but there is a certain assumption in our culture that technology is and always will be a democratizing force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true, for example, that the prospect of uterus transplant to trans women trouble cisgender discourses of motherhood, and likewise, discourses of womanhood that are predicated on mothering or the ability therein. But who gets these uteruses? Where do they come from? Already, we have technology to assist in (trans) reproduction. But as I have shown, cultural discourses around motherhood, transness, and law already intersect to already deny trans women access to those technologies. When appropriately medicalized and class-privileged trans women are the only trans women able to employ these technologies, trans family making ends up reinforces part of the narrative it purports to destabilize, i.e. that cisnormative and economically privileged people are the most appropriate parents. Similarly, the prospect of these same cisnormative and economically privileged trans women gaining access to surgically transplanted uteruses serves to strengthen the cisnormativity of their bodies and lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I propose is that trans reproductive justice has an opportunity to move beyond the technology of reproduction (“high” technology and body technology, i.e. wombs) and onto the sociality of reproduction, wherein genetic input is not a necessary part parenthood, and wherein trans people do not face discrimination and ridicule as parents. I do not mean to suggest that barriers to access this technology are not important sites of activism, but rather an acknowledgement that these are not the only barriers to reproduction and reproductive justice broadly, equally for trans people and cisgender people, and that broader coalitions are possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baetens, Patricia, M. Camus, and P. Devroey. 2003. “Should Requests for Donor Insemination on Social Grounds Be Expanded to Transsexuals?” Reproductive BioMedicine Online (Reproductive Healthcare Limited) 6 (3): 281.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faccio, Elena, Elena Bordin, and Sabrina Cipolletta. 2013. “Transsexual Parenthood and New Role Assumptions.” Culture, Health &amp;amp; Sexuality 15 (9): 1055–70. https://doi.org/10.1080/13691058.2013.806676.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hammer, Gail. 2015. “Transparent: When Legal Fictions and Judicial Imagination Make Facts Disappear, They Enforce Transphobic Discrimination.” Columbia Journal of Gender and Law 30 (January): 119.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Littman, Lisa. 2018. “Rapid-Onset Gender Dysphoria in Adolescents and Young Adults: A Study of Parental Reports.” PLoS ONE 13 (8): 1–41. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0202330.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nixon, Laura. 2013. “The Right to (Trans) Parent: A Reproductive Justice Approach to Reproductive Rights, Fertility, and Family-Building Issues Facing Transgender People.” William &amp;amp; Mary Journal of Women &amp;amp; the Law 20 (1): 73–103.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smith, Tory. 2016. “Beyond Visibiltiy: The Call for Transgender Reproductive Justice.” Huffington Post (blog). April 21, 2016. https://www.huffingtonpost.com/tory-smith/beyond-visibiltiy-the-cal_b_9748572.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strangio, Chase. 2015. “Can Reproductive Trans Bodies Exist?” CUNY Law Review 19: 223.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wierckx, Katrien, Isabelle Stuyver, Steven Weyers, Alaa Hamada, Ashok Agarwal, Petra De Sutter, and Guy T’Sjoen. 2012. “Sperm Freezing in Transsexual Women.” Archives Of Sexual Behavior 41 (5): 1069–71. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10508-012-0012-x.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexandra Chace</name></author><summary type="html">This essay was originally presented at the National Women’s Studies Association conference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are All Women Angry About This? Notes on Identity Politics and Affective Solidarities</title><link href="https://alexchace.com/affective_solidarities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are All Women Angry About This? Notes on Identity Politics and Affective Solidarities" /><published>2018-11-05T07:50:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-05T07:50:00-05:00</updated><id>https://alexchace.com/affective_solidarities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alexchace.com/affective_solidarities/">&lt;p&gt;The Kavanaugh hearings brought forth a battery of rhetoric about what women &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; and what women &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;, both in liberal feminist and explicitly anti-feminist terms. In an opinion piece for &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, feminist author Rebecca Traister claims that “women were incandescent with rage and sorrow and horror…getting angry in a new way, a public way, an unapologetic way” (Traister 2018). Beyond her personal feelings, Traister reports having seen “hundreds of messages from women who reported the same experience, of finding themselves awash in tears” in response to Dr. Ford’s account before the U.S. Senate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, too, saw these same messages repeated, across social media, from friends, colleagues, influencers, even politicians. &lt;em&gt;Women are angry. Women are hurt. Women are horrified&lt;/em&gt;. I thought to myself: &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; women? I do not mean to imply that I do not consider Justice Kavanaugh’s actions morally objectionable, or that I am pleased with his appointment to the Supreme Court. But I was not angry, nor was I hurt. In fact, I felt utterly resentful of the many feminists who were all too eager to use the occasion to shore up women’s solidarity along lines of identity with universalist and occasionally essential rhetoric, and, in my view, much of this rhetoric had a totalizing effect, in which my own experiences were politically subservient to and eclipsed by those of affluent and heterosexual women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I was confused. Do women truly feel in any particular way? Am I a “bad feminist” because I refuse certain feminist political imperatives to feel and act a certain way? If women are meant to feel in one particular way in that they are women, and this can be assessed positively, what, exactly, is the “feel” of being a woman? If this feeling of being a woman eludes me, do I continue to be a woman? Or am I man, in-between, or something else entirely because of my failure to cope with the political box of womanhood? And perhaps more insidiously, is my cynicism how patriarchy “means” for me to feel, i.e. am I being “duped” into supporting its political agenda to excuse sexual assault over my “natural” feminist allegiances?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, I am deeply uncomfortable with the project of identity and its politics, to the point that I almost always find identity stifling, restrictive, and, more often than not, utterly incomprehensible. Lately I have been deeply apathetic and, perhaps, distrustful, of any political movement that seeks to provide any particular understanding of what women &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;, how women &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;, or indeed any that posit a notion of ‘woman’ that implies a shared experience or standpoint. I am, however, also aware of the specific political circumstances that drive the invocation of identity in experiential terms, and, despite my misgivings, I am deeply sympathetic to the efforts of feminists who, like Traister (2018), consider it politically favorable to build feminist solidarities that invoke the (apparent) shared experience or emotionality of womanhood. Here, I wish to account for my trepidations concerning feminist politics through a brief relation of the interplay between emotion, gender, and identity, as well as the perils and prospects that this interplay offers in terms of (de)stabilizing essentially and experientially female political organizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Unnatural Emotions: Everyday Sentiments on a Micronesian Atoll &amp;amp; Their Challenge to Western Theory&lt;/em&gt;, Catherine Lutz (1998) illustrates a discourse of Western emotion that concerns itself “with emotion as essence; whether the passions are portrayed as aspects of a divinely inspired human nature or as genetically encoded biological fact, they remain, to varying degrees, things that have an inherent and unchanging nature“ (Lutz 1998, 53). Lutz (1998) argues for a broader interpretation of emotions as produced and implicated within certain sociocultural systems. In her view, much like gender or sexual orientation, “…emotion is seen as a component of individuals rather than of social situations or relationships, the discipline and methods of psychology have been taken as most appropriate for its study” (Lutz 1998, 41). Again, like gender or sexual identity, Western theories of emotion therefore posit an “inner truth” to emotion that we must “come out” with by disclosing that “I am angry”, that “I am gay”, or that “I am a woman”. Often, each of these statements implicate the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, Traister (2018) claims that “female anger is discouraged, &lt;em&gt;repressed&lt;/em&gt;, ignored, &lt;em&gt;swallowed&lt;/em&gt;” (Traister 2018, emphasis mine). With this mind, she encourages women to “come out” with their anger as a political weapon against sexism. But if this assertion that women’s anger has been “swallowed” and “repressed” is true, does this not suggest an interiority of emotion that contradicts Lutz’s critiques of Western theory? A Foucauldian perspective would suggest that this silence around women’s anger is a central part of the discourse itself, producing dichotomous (gendered) emotionalities. Indeed, in &lt;em&gt;The History of Sexuality&lt;/em&gt;, Foucault (1978) explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no binary division to be made between what one says and what one does not say; we must try to determine the different ways of not saying such things, how those who can and those who cannot speak of them are distributed, which type of discourse is authorized, or which form of discretion is required in either case. There is not one but many silences, and they are an integral part of the strategies that underlie and permeate discourses. (Foucault 1978, 27)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Traister (2018), perhaps unknowingly, allows for such a Foucauldian reading of emotional productivity when she suggests that, rather than “fully” repressed, female anger may be “…transformed into something more palatable, and less recognizable as fury — something like tears” (Traister 2018). But if women are &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; wielding our anger in these terms, what, exactly, is Traister asking us to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand Traister’s claims in normative terms. Traister asks us to wield a specific political anger, performed in its explicitly masculine terms. Rather than how women &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;, her focus is on how women &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; feel, not in terms of particular emotions, but particular performances. She explains that Judge Kavanaugh “cry[ed] and yell[ed]”, that Lindsey Graham “rant[ed]”, and that “women are beginning to behave that way too” (Traister 2018). In other words, women are beginning to, and ought to perform their anger publicly &lt;em&gt;like men&lt;/em&gt;. But just because women are behaving this way does not mean that women are doing so universally, or that their message is perceived as universally the same. Likewise, Kavanaugh and Graham being “allowed” to cry and yell does not mean that all men can do so without recourse. Lutz (1998) suggests, emotion “exists in a system of power relations and plays a role in maintaining it” (Lutz 1998, 54). Emotional performance, then, is mediated and translated by intersubjective relations of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Echoing Lutz, Richard &amp;amp; Rudnyckyj (2009) “conceive of affect not so much as an object circulating among subjects, but rather as a medium in which subjects circulate” (Richard &amp;amp; Rudnyckyj 2009, 59). As such, “emotion occupies an important place in Western gender ideologies” because the “ideological subordination of women” is realized “in identifying emotion primarily with irrationality, subjectivity, the chaotic, and other negative characteristics, and in subsequently labeling women the emotional gender” (Lutz 1998, 54). In this case, women’s performance of anger is intersubjective, and a sign/signified relationship is not a reliable interpretation of emotion, due to the predisposition of certain signs to invoke particular interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regard to this intersubjectivity, gender theorist Judith Butler (1990) introduces a specific “provisionality” to discourses of identity. In her view, “[t]o claim that this is what I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; is to suggest a provisional totalization of this “I”” (Butler 2010, 309). Identities, then, produce “a certain radical &lt;em&gt;concealment&lt;/em&gt;” when we attempt to “disclose the true and full content of that “I”” (Butler 2010, 309). Speaking of lesbian identity, Butler explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…it is always finally unclear what is meant by invoking the lesbian-signifier, since its signification is always to some degree out of one’s control, but also because its &lt;em&gt;specificity&lt;/em&gt; can only be demarcated by exclusions that return to disrupt its claim to coherence. What, if anything, can lesbians be said to share? (Butler 2010, 309)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Butler’s radical concealment need not be confined to identity, rather, there is also a radical concealment when we “come out” with our emotions. In calling for anger narrowly, Traister necessarily precludes sadness, happiness, fear, and any number of other politically disadvantageous emotions. But there are also political dangers in these preclusions. Butler rightly questions “[w]hat or who is it that is “out,” made manifest and fully disclosed, when and if I reveal myself as lesbian? What is it that is now known, anything?” (Butler 2010, 309). I mean to suggest that it is impossible to account for all possible readings of our performances of anger, no matter how personally or politically harmful they may become. Assertive or angry women, already the “emotional gender,” run the risk of dismissal as “bitches” or “hysterics”. They may also be taken as jokes, and their anger may incite laughter and ridicule. For some of us, anger will be sexualized and fetishized. For others, anger may be taken as aggression, and incite violent responses against black and brown bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not necessary that we perform our anger in exactly the same manner or for identical reasons, and I believe, despite these dangers, the provisionality of emotions still offers new opportunities for disruption and play. Richard &amp;amp; Rudnyckyj (2009) argue that affect is “mutually constitutive”, meaning that subjects obtain cultural intelligibility through the many affective mimetic processes in which they are engaged. In Butlerian terms, the mimetic processes of emotionality stabilize identity (and therefore emotion) as mutually intelligible categories of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traister’s unladylike anger fails to perform normative gender both in rendering women as unintelligible within the heterosexual matrix and renders women mutually intelligible to those who share our political imperatives. Sara Ahmed argues that “emotions do things, and they align individuals with communities—or bodily space with social space—through the very intensity of their attachments” (Ahmed 2004, 119). In this view, women’s anger could serve as a means to solidarity in its alignment of individuals, regardless of experience or gender, with a broader affective feminist community. Consider that unlike identity, solidarity based on shared affective affinity does not necessarily totalize women’s experiences or define them in any specific terms. As a result, affective solidarity &lt;em&gt;queers&lt;/em&gt; normative identarian politics insofar as it resists intelligibility within cultural systems of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hochschild (2003) suggests that “[w]e assess the “appropriateness” of a feeling by making a comparison between feeling and situation” (Hochschild 2003, 94). In this situation, the assessor is lent “a “normal” yardstick - a socially normal one” (Hochschild 2003, 94). Whereas, following Foucault, identity categories arise to grade legibility in reference to the social yardstick (the Norm), affective feminist politics also queer gender in part through their confusion of situationally appropriate and categorically legible behavior. But as I have shown, affective solidarity may still provide the minimal legibility that communal organizing prerequires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit that I am still uncomfortable risking the restating of ‘woman’ as a political category, regardless of the terms. Following French feminist and philosopher Michèle Le Dœuff (2000), I distinguish a “feminism of equality”, which makes no assumptions about the eternality or homogeneity of ‘woman’, from a “feminism of difference”, which seeks to provide a language through which “women can speak their sex” (Le Dœuff 2000, 51-52). For Le Dœuff, the feminists of difference wish to “feel” themselves to be a notion of ‘woman’ that is ultimately reduced to sameness (Le Dœuff 2000, 44, 53). I fear that affective solidarity risks being read as a new strategy for women to &lt;em&gt;feel like&lt;/em&gt; women, or to “speak their sex”, thereby reifying an interiority of womanhood that I do not believe exists in real terms. I also fear that this essentialism precludes the kind of coalitional non-identarian feminist organizing that affective solidarity allows in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just as Butler chooses to “appear at political occasions under the sign of lesbian,” though she “would like to have it permanently unclear what precisely that sign signifies,” I, too, choose to appear provisionally under the signs of ‘woman’ and ‘feminist’ for political purposes, provided no interiority can be ascertained (Butler 2010, 308). The non-essential promise of affective feminist solidarity opens up space for social, political, and historical differences between individuals (regardless of gender) &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the need for reconciliation with or repression of any particular feminist political image. When “woman” as a category eludes designation and refuses legibility, we begin to consider opportunities for non-experiential coalitional movement-building that transcends normative paradigms of what and who we are, thereby allowing a more appropriate assessment of what we &lt;em&gt;could be&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; women/men but &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; women and men.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sara Ahmed. “Affective Economies.” Social Text 22, no. 2 (2004): 117-139. https://muse.jhu.edu/ (accessed November 3, 2018).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butler, Judith P., and Sara Salih. The Judith Butler Reader. Malden, MA: Blackwell, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foucault, Michel. 1990. The History of Sexuality. New York : Vintage Books, 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hochshild, Arlie. The Commercialization of Intimate Life. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le Dœuff, Michèle. 2000. “Hipparchia’s Choice” In French Feminism Reader, edited by Kelly Oliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boston, MA: Rowman &amp;amp; Littlefield Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lutz, Catherine A. Unnatural Emotions: Everyday Sentiments on a Micronesian Atoll &amp;amp; Their Challenge to Western Theory. Chicago, IL: Univ. of Chicago Press, 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard, A. and Rudnyckyj, D. (2009), Economies of affect. Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute, 15: 57-77. doi:10.1111/j.1467-9655.2008.01530.x&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traister. Rebecca. Fury Is a Political Weapon. And Women Need to Wield It in The New York Times, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alexandra Chace</name></author><summary type="html">The Kavanaugh hearings brought forth a battery of rhetoric about what women feel and what women are, both in liberal feminist and explicitly anti-feminist terms. In an opinion piece for The New York Times, feminist author Rebecca Traister claims that “women were incandescent with rage and sorrow and horror…getting angry in a new way, a public way, an unapologetic way” (Traister 2018). Beyond her personal feelings, Traister reports having seen “hundreds of messages from women who reported the same experience, of finding themselves awash in tears” in response to Dr. Ford’s account before the U.S. Senate.</summary></entry></feed>